Let's come back to Mount Pleasant. For
people who don't have the historical
context, what were the Mount Pleasant
riots? And you said right before I asked
about the test, you said it was great.
And if that is actually not a sarcastic
statement, but a real sort of statement
of how you felt, I want to know why that
was the case. But let's start with just
a little bit of
history for people who who aren't
familiar. I certainly wasn't with the
Mount Pleasant riots.
>> When I said it was great in terms of
being a rookie right out of the academy
and understanding you've got yourself
into,
>> Right.
>> here's what you've got yourself into,
right? Like you went to work today and
you're not going home for 5 days, you
know. So, the night before my first day
out of the academy, there was a pair of
police officers walking a foot patrol in
in our patrol district. They tried to
place a gentleman under arrest for
drinking in public. He was
Latino male, didn't speak English. We
had a big problem in our city back in
those days. Law enforcement, we had very
few people in the department that spoke
Spanish. We had a huge Latino
population. There was a big gap in our
community. So, it's really difficult to
do any kind of effective policing if
you're not communicating with the people
in the community and we were not. So,
when this officer was trying to place
this person under arrest, during the
handcuffing, the the subject after one
handcuff is on, he turned around, pulled
a knife on the officer. The officer
shot. So, he was shot with one handcuff
on. So, the partner of the officer shot
rolled him over, put the other handcuff
on, took the knife away, called
paramedics. All the people saw was a
handcuffed person who'd been shot.
>> Mhm.
>> So, the Latino community in that
neighborhood immediately began, you
know,
gathering on the street, large crowd.
This all happened around 11:30 at night.
So, by the time I got into the station
for 5:30 roll call, I show up at 5:30 in
the morning, the riot had broken out
around 1:00 a.m. They had burned several
police cars. There was stores that were
looted and on fire. And it was a big,
big deal down in Mount Pleasant. So,
when I got to work my first day, I
walked into the station said, "Hi, I'm
Cathy Lanier. I'm the, you know, new
rookie from the academy." And they threw
me a gas mask and they told me to go out
and get in the van. They said, "Hop over
the counter, go out the back door and
get in that van." And I was like,
"Okay."
So, I hopped over the counter and went
and got in the van. I was sitting with
15 other cops with gas masks on and big
riot sticks and they took us down and
they dumped us off on the corner of
Mount Pleasant Park Road and it was
fully engulfed in a fires and looting
and, you know, people were throwing
bottles and bricks and stones at us. We
had little helmets they had given us in
the as we were hopping out of the van.
And I didn't have a radio cuz rookies
weren't allowed to have radios at the
time, right? I had not been trained how
to use the radio. So, my partner had the
radio. So, my lifeline was on my
partner. But, we stood there online and
literally got pelted with bricks and
bottles and I mean, over the course of 5
days. It was trial by fire, for sure.
But, it was a big learning experience
for me because I understood the
frustration. I understood the
frustration. The large number of that
whole community in Mount Pleasant were
all Latino. They didn't speak English.
The cops didn't speak to them very well.
I mean, nobody could really communicate
with but the cops were
pushing people around and there was no
way to to try and get the story straight
and really no effort to get the story
straight, right? To understand
the frustration. So, it was a big
learning experience for me as I worked
my way up the ranks to understand how
important inclusion is in the community.
If you're a police officer and you are
not embedding yourself in that community
and understanding who the people are in
that community and what their needs are
and how to communicate, you're really
not going to be successful.
>> We're going to, I imagine, revisit that
at some point cuz it seems to be a
consistent thread through a lot of the
work they've done. But I want to spend a
little bit more time on Mount Pleasant.
I am curious
I suppose yet again what that
maybe showed you about yourself or just
highlighted about you constitutionally
or personality-wise, right? Because
I would imagine some people could get
dropped in that environment after they
just signed up. They're like, "Hey, I'm
just here for tuition reimbursement.
Holy [__] Like I'm I'm getting hit with
bricks. Like this is not exactly what I
thought my first day was going to be."
And they're out, right? Like I have to
imagine that there are some people who
would be closer to that. Maybe they
didn't quit, but they're probably closer
to that end of the spectrum.
And
do you thrive in particular in intense
environments? I wonder, right? Because
like in my case, constitutionally sort
of out of the box, little things,
especially interpersonal things,
bother me that are kind of trivial,
frankly. Like I get all wound up about
very stupid things. But in crisis
situations,
you know, the car accident in front of
me, some guy's got his like leg blown
apart or whatever, I actually do really
I do very well in those environments. I
don't know why that is. I really have no
idea.
>> Yeah.
>> But was there anything that you noticed
about yourself in that type of
environment, in those types of
circumstances?
>> I think the thing for me that I thrive
on is as we're dropped out down there
and they're giving us the riot sticks
and the helmets and the gas mask and
they're shooting canisters of gas into
the crowd and you knowing what started
this and how it has all blew up, I'm
thinking to myself, we're not going
about this the right way. Like I was a
rookie, I know nothing about policing
other than what I was taught in the
academy. So by no means did I think I
was smarter than the guy making the
command decisions, right? But I'm just
looking at it from my perspective going,
this is just not the right way to do
this. Like this is we're not going to
win here. It's this is not a win
situation. This should be done
differently and I just always felt like
from the minute I hit the ground like
watching I like to analyze the way that
we were doing things and thinking why
are we doing this this way? There's a
better way to do these things and so
that's the way I felt in Mount Pleasant
my first day on the job. You know, it's
really hard to explain I just felt like
there's a problem to be solved here and
we're not going about it in a
problem-solving manner. We're going
about it with brute force, right? Brute
force doesn't always work.
>> Mhm.
>> So it intrigued me. Every day after that
once the riots were over, I started
walking a foot beat in the city.
Every single day I went to work I got to
problem-solve for
six, seven, eight times a day, you know,
I'm calls for service, 911 calls you
responded, people who are in crisis,
people who need help and you know, you
get to try and help think through that,
help solve the problem and that's that's
what I enjoyed doing. It's frustrating
when you're at the bottom of the totem
pole when you're the line officer,
right? You're in a chain of command you
can't make certain decisions, but
I did feel like every single day I went
to work I made a difference in someone's
life.
>> Mhm.
>> No matter how small.